Welcome back.
Remember how I said there
wasn't one exact formula or
template to follow when
conducting retrospectives?
That's because every team learns,
adapts, and grows differently.
In this video, we'll talk about
how to conduct a retrospective.
Different situations call for different
tactics, and when it comes to receiving
potentially sensitive feedback,
it's best to consider your team's needs.
There are a couple of things to keep in
mind before you begin a retrospective.
First, you'll want to maintain
a positive tone throughout the process.
Remember, even if there are some
tough conversations, the objective of
a retrospective is to encourage
improvements, which prepare you for
future projects.
In general, the retrospective should be
considered a positive experience where
team members feel comfortable
sharing their feedback.
Next, you may need to be considerate
of teams outside of your own.
If there are other teams
you partner with regularly,
they'll need to be involved
in the retrospective, as well.
For instance,
some adjacent teams that were part of the
project may feel like they want to voice
an opinion about the struggle to
maintain communication between teams.
If they choose not to be
involved in the retrospective,
you'll at least want to share
your findings with them.
After all,
smoothing cross-team interactions and
deliverable handoffs is a frequent
topic of discussion in retrospectives.
As previously mentioned,
you can use various props and
tools to conduct your retrospective.
Here's an example of what
a retrospective might entail.
As you'll notice, it's pretty extensive
and includes a lot of opportunity for
details. You'll want to encourage as much
feedback as possible from your team.
This retrospective template is a standard
document, with room for project managers
to fill out and discuss with their
teams and use it to guide the conversation.
Go over the chain of events in the same
way that they happened in real time.
What happened during the planning stage?
What could have gone better?
Where did your team get lucky?
How about during the execution stage?
As you do that, fill out the lessons
learned section, which is a space for
you to elaborate on things you could
do differently the next time around.
This is a space to include which risks
materialized during your project.
Was there a large gap between
the original plan and its execution?
How did the team feel about it?
Maybe several of your project team members
commented on the fact that the website
launch didn't meet the original deadline.
Because of this, sales team members
didn't hit their numbers that month,
the marketing department had to change the
date on several pieces of content and ads,
and the sponsor had to answer to investors
who were eager to view the website.
Team members are upset now because if you
had prioritized the website's completion
and spent less time on less important
tasks, this may have been avoided.
It's difficult feedback,
but it's pertinent for
future successes to consider
why this risk materialised.
Next time, you'll make sure to prioritize
a task with so many dependencies.
Now that you've gone over how everything
went, build a better future for
your team by filling out
the remaining tables.
The first one is action items and will
address the question "What action should
we take as a result of our lessons learned?" You'll start on the left-hand side
with the action items you want to address,
then make your way through the cells to
the right as you include information
like: type—as in, is this a tool,
a process, a team, or something else?
Owner—who will own this action item?
And relative links—consider where
we're tracking this item.
The next table is all about
future considerations.
Are there any risks that could
become issues if not addressed
in the next quarter?
Do you need to pass off ownership
of this project to someone else?
Include those and make sure to fill
out the other cells, including:
Type—is this a process,
a team, or something else?
Contact—who can be a resource
on this procedure
if we need to reference it later?
And again, any links that may seem
relevant to this topic. that could be
relevant documentation if you're
passing the project off or
maybe a risk register from your
project. And there you have it.
Now, I showed you a pretty standard
retrospective as you'd fill it out,
but if you feel like your team needs
something a little more interactive,
feel free to have fun with it.
The way you gather this information from
your team can be more innovative than
just a list.
You can use color coding,
sticky notes, columns with emojis, and
anything else you feel will suit
your team and keep them engaged.
Whatever you do, make sure you carry the
lessons learned into your next projects.
In the next video, we'll recap all of our
own lessons learned from this module.
Meet you there!